All right, everyone.
Today,
I have very great news.
We are about to speak with our first coordinator on mainnet.
So if you guys were following Crunch a couple of weeks back,
we introduced this new role
on testnet called the coordinators.
Coordinators are other entities in the world of decentralized AI
that would like to tap into the power of Crunch.
And the first coordinator that reached mainnet, meaning that
managed to develop the smart contract necessary
to interact with Crunch
is called Synth
and I am here in New York with his founder,
James.
How are you, James?
It's great to have you here.
Today,
the main subject is the Synth coordinator.
So first and foremost.
What are you guys building?
James.
On this subnet
and
what kind of product are you actually putting out
out of Synth?
It's super exciting because we are particularly fan of these
approaches that are more probabilistic instead of
you know, predicting price.
And actually,
I don't agree.
A lot of people make that mistake and try to predict price
and end up in this
very very noisy environment that is extremely hard to model.
Whereas here you had two layers.
Not only you try to predict a distribution of price,
but you also had many vectors with many
researchers
and so my next question would be:
How did you end up in this setup?
Why did you choose to go for decentralized AI setup?
And why is it making so much sense for a product like Synth?
It's a very complex problem to solve.
I think people don't realize that
when you come in the market and you try to build a quant algorithm
or you try to predict market,
you actually compete with
a huge team of quant and researchers
with other companies that are injecting millions,
if not hundreds of millions every year
to mine every little bit of information that can help them
trying to understand what will be this distribution of returns and etc.
And so I think in your setup there is not only the stability
but also the predictive power and alpha that you can get from there.
Because you can attract people from
vast different background and by the way
guys you don't need to understand finance to do
and to compete at Crunch.
At Crunch and at Synth
on the coordinator of Synth on Crunch,
it's just pure price distribution like:
You look at time series, kinda.
Of course you can inject a lot of
other kinda feature, maybe that's something you wanna touch base.
We didn't talk about the scoring.
You mentioned the reward.
Maybe quick word on the scoring.
How do you assess the best submission?
What is the scoring metrics?
And how do you really
prevail on top of people that try to actually cheat the subnet
or cheat the coordinator.
It's live scoring.
It's the best protection against any kind of cheating.
Right?
We were having this discussion before where we said:
"Okay, you can have a very hard training
you're going to be scored on live data on a live ring
with everyone else looking at you."
And so if you fake the training or you overfit, you know, the data set
you're going to get destroyed on the ring.
There is no shortcut.
Live market is there to test your algorithm
the way you would have been scored on a proper trading strategy.
And on top of that you have...
I guess people can choose their strategy
but you have these negative incentives in the mining slots
and so guys don't worry because I know you're not used to that.
Crunch is working a lot on reputation for a long time.
So we will kinda help people
in building meta model out of all the submission on Crunch
and then submit these meta models into mining slots.
Except of course if someone is really performing alone on Crunch
then we probably plug-in directly
into Synth.
In the end, Crunch tries to solve that.
The complexity of opening a mining slot,
paying for the mining slot
maybe you can try more things on Crunch, 'cause you wanna have
the time to test, and the money
that you're gonna lose
so you can be a bit more creative maybe
and end up participating in mining without the negative incentive.
You still have to build your reputation on Crunch.
For that reason we have this one month warm-up
during which we will just look at the submission and the model
before actually starting registering mining slots
into Synth.
Exciting, but not easy.
So we started to look a bit at the
what was the performance of the different miner on your subnet.
And your product will be as good as
the best prediction or the best ensemble you can have over there.
Because that's very, this kind of anchor of a price that
then allows you to build whatever you could on top.
The level is pretty high and you had one good archetype
of that performance with what you did on prediction market.
That I think is just brilliant.
Do you want to talk about it?
Real player coming in.
You mentioned that point in particular.
You mentioned discrepancy,
like you figure out something that is interesting,
I think the anecdote.
I think the outcome of that,
the proof that you have is you've been correctly predicting
the direction of one of the assets you're tracking, for like
a certain amount of time,
like to take that icon from that point to where you end up.
Okay, prediction markets aren't perfect
and there's plenty of ways to game that.
But cool article guys, by the way, go and check it out.
I think you published it on your Twitter.
So taking it from there,
where do you see...
you mentioned like option pricing, you mentioned
retail traders...
Where do you see Synth going?
Where do you see most traction?
New York Stock Exchange announced last week.
We didn't have it in 2025.
We've been crypto since like maybe 10 years.
I'm used to seeing markets going on weekend anyway.
So maybe last word on that.
So we're going to mine in this coordinator
probabilistic return of a few cryptocurrencies.
Precious metals.
A few equity as well.
Right now, where do you see the -
Are you going to add more time series or more assets?
At which speed?
How do you move forward with that?
The Crunchers that are listening:
What kind of tips you can give?
What do you think the most performing miners are actually doing?
Fitting a famous president, right?
And so right now within the game.
We're going to be providing data from Pyth, right?
What kind of data are you providing natively?
That's a new feature on Crunch, by the way.
Synth is going to be the first time guys where,
when you submit your model into the TEE
you'll be able to also access external data.
So you can have kind of API calls
within the trusted execution environment
and fetch data from
I don't know, maybe you have a proprietary data set somewhere.
Maybe you have some
scraping that you have been doing here and there.
Or maybe you have a validator in this particular protocol
I don't know if you already have, SOL is not yet into...
You have Ethereum, Bitcoin and?
Okay perfect, maybe you're running some application that runs that.
Maybe you're deep into some other networks
and you have some information.
I'm sure some people
would love to be able to do that and that's a first on Crunch.
We needed to do anyway because there is
only limited amount of alpha in price data, right?
We said it's been massively mined anyway.
So maybe you can go deeper with models
but I think it's better to go orthogonal and find new ideas
on your data sets, on your feature set
All right, James. This is super exciting.
We are extremely happy. I think it's -
We could not dream about a better coordinator here.
It's really aligned with what we like, what we believe in.
There is massive rewards, guys.
We talk about like $100K a month.
So it's unseen.
But also very competitive.
But we like that anyway.
Guys, I really encourage you if you are a trader, a trading desk,
if you need some pricing data,
I think Synth is going to provide some very, very interesting vectors
and great insight in your trading infrastructure
or in your strat.
Check this out on their website.
If you are a Cruncher in the coming days
maybe it's already released by the moment we release this video
you should see on crunchdao.com/competition/synth
the Synth competition. We're gonna open a Discord channel
where we will be able to exchange and ask questions and etc.
Feel free to go and join James' community
as well on their own Discord
if you want to go deeper.
But I think after the first months of warm-up
would be great to have you again
and maybe check out where we actually are on the leaderboard
and start Phase 2 with the mining operation.
All right, let's go.
Good day everyone.
Bye-bye.